<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- ***************************************************************************
 * Copyright (c) 2009 - 2010 eXXcellent solutions gmbh and others.
 * All rights reserved. This program and the accompanying materials
 * are made available under the terms of the Eclipse Public License v1.0
 * which accompanies this distribution, and is available at
 * http://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html
 *
 ******************************************************************************/

@author Achim Demelt - Initial contribution
 
-->

<chapter id="incrementalGeneration">
  <title>Incremental Generation</title>

  <para>
    As projects become larger, so typically do their models. However, the larger
    the models are, the longer the code generation process takes. In a mature
    project, a developer typically changes only a small part of a large model.
    Performing a full code generation process for the whole model slows down the
    development cycle considerably due to various factors:
    
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        The whole model must be traversed, and each statement in the Xpand
        templates must be executed. The larger the model is and the more Xpand
        templates you have, the higher the negative impact is.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        All generated files are written to disk. The I/O operation itself is
        one major contributor to the overall elapsed time. What's more, files
        are typically post-processed by beautifiers, which is another time
        consuming operation. If you are working with protected regions, the
        impact is even more dramatic.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Since every file has a new timestamp after code generation, typically
        a compiler will pick up these new files and start compilation, which
        adds more CPU and I/O cycles to the process.
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    Considering that for a small change in the model only a fraction of the
    generated files actually do change their contents, performing a full
    generation is obviously a waste of time.
  </para>
  
  <para>
    Beginning with the Helios release train (Eclipse 3.6, Xpand 0.8), Xpand
    now ships with an incremental generation facility. This works very similar
    to the incremental Java compiler in Eclipse. It detects which parts of a
    model have changed since the last generation process. It then
    determines which files need to be generated due to that change and which
    are unaffected by it. Only the former are the regenerated, while the
    latter remain untouched.
  </para>
  
  <para>
    The following sections explain how this incremental generation feature
    works and how you can use it.
  </para>

  <section id="incrementalGeneration_background">
    <title>Technical Background</title>
    
    <para>
      The key to incremental generation lies in knowing which element in a model
      was used to generate which file. This information can easily be computed
      during generation, by tracking which parts of the model are
      accessed in the context of any given
      <code>«FILE»</code> statement. A callback for the
      Xpand generator does this job and builds up a so-called
      <emphasis>trace model</emphasis> on-the-fly.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      The second important information is the actual change that has occurred
      in a model. There are basically two ways to compute this. One is to
      attach a change listener when editing the model and capture the change
      as it happens. The other way is to keep a backup copy of the model and
      compare the old version with the current version to compute the change.
      See <xref linkend="incrementalGeneration_performance" />
      for pros and cons of each of the two ways. In either
      case, the result is a so-called <emphasis>diff model</emphasis>.
    </para>
        
    <para>
      When we know which parts of a model have changed, and we also know which
      files have been produced based upon these parts of the model, we can then
      skip the generation of all other files, thus performing incremental
      generation.
    </para>    
  </section>

  <section id="incrementalGeneration_usage">
    <title>Using Incremental Generation</title>

    <section id="incrementalGeneration_usage_facade">
      <title>The Incremental Generation Facade</title>
      
      <para>
        The easiest way to benefit from incremental generation is to use the
        <emphasis>IncrementalGenerationFacade</emphasis> workflow component:
      </para>

<programlisting>
&lt;workflow&gt;
  &lt;component id="incremental"
      class="org.eclipse.xpand2.incremental.IncrementalGenerationFacade"&gt;
    &lt;newModelFile value="path/to/your/model.file" /&gt;
    &lt;oldModelFile value="path/to/backup/model.file" /&gt;
    &lt;traceModelFile value="path/to/store/trace/model.trace" /&gt; 
    &lt;outlet path="path/to/your/outlet/" overwrite="true"/&gt;
  &lt;/component&gt;

  &lt;component id="generator" class="org.eclipse.xpand2.Generator"&gt;
    &lt;expand value="your::template::Root FOR model" /&gt;
    &lt;outlet path="temp/" overwrite="true"/&gt;
    &lt;metaModel class="org.eclipse.xtend.typesystem.emf.EmfRegistryMetaModel" /&gt;
    &lt;vetoableCallback idRef="incremental" /&gt;
  &lt;/component&gt;
&lt;/workflow&gt;
</programlisting>
    
      <para>
        The <emphasis>IncrementalGenerationFacade</emphasis> takes four
        parameters:
        
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The <emphasis>newModelFile</emphasis> is the file
              path where the model to generate is stored. This file is stored
              in a model slot named <emphasis>model</emphasis>
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The <emphasis>oldModelFile</emphasis> is the file
              path where a copy of the previous state of the model is stored.
              The model is automatically copied to this location after the
              generation process and kept between generator invocations.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The <emphasis>traceModelFile</emphasis> is the file
              path where the <emphasis>trace model</emphasis> of the generation
              process is stored between generator invocations.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              A regular <emphasis>outlet</emphasis> list that must match the
              one given for the regular generator invocation.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        
        The <emphasis>IncrementalGenerationFacade</emphasis> component must then
        be passed as a <emphasis>vetoableCallback</emphasis> parameter to the
        invocation of the Xpand <emphasis>Generator</emphasis>.
      </para>

      <para>
        With the simple workflow given above, you should be able to observe
        that for any given change in the model, only the files affected by
        that change are regenerated, while all others remain untouched. Even
        deleting elements will result in specific (previously generated) files
        being deleted from the hard disk.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Note that you have to use file paths for all models because they
        are physically copied on the hard disk. Passing locations that
        can only be resolved from the classpath is not possible.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="incrementalGeneration_usage_callback">
      <title>The Incremental Generation Callback</title>
      
      <para>
        While the <emphasis>IncrementalGenerationFacade</emphasis> is easy
        to use, it is rather restricted in its capabilities and fixed in the
        operations it performs. Using the
        <emphasis>IncrementalGenerationCallback</emphasis> gives you more
        control over the steps involved. A typical workflow for incremental
        generation needs to perform the following tasks:
        
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Read the (current) model into a slot.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Read the previous state of the model into another slot. This
              may, of course, not exist, e.g. for the very first invocation.
              Full generation must be performed in this case.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Compute the changes between the two versions of the model
              (if possible) and
              put that <emphasis>diff model</emphasis> into a slot.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Read the <emphasis>trace model</emphasis> computed during the
              previous generator invocation and put it into a slot.
              As with the old state of the model, this may not exist, which
              also leads to full generation.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Initialize the <emphasis>IncrementalGenerationCallback</emphasis>
              with the <emphasis>diff model</emphasis> and the
              <emphasis>trace model</emphasis>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Run the Xpand <emphasis>Generator</emphasis> component with
              the <emphasis>IncrementalGenerationCallback</emphasis>.              
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Clean obsolete files, i.e. files that need to be deleted because
              the corresponding elements in the model have been deleted.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Write the new <emphasis>trace model</emphasis> computed during
              code generation to the hard disk so that it is available
              for the next generation process.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Make a backup copy of the model so that it can be compared with
              the next version upon subsequent generator invocation.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </para>

      <para>
        This is a sample workflow that performs all these steps:
      </para>
      
<programlisting>
&lt;workflow&gt;
  &lt;!-- read new model --&gt;
  &lt;component id="modelreader" class="org.eclipse.emf.mwe.utils.Reader"
    uri="model/my.model"
    firstElementOnly="true"
    modelSlot="model"               
  /&gt;
  &lt;!-- read old model, copied from previous run. may not exist, so ignore missing model --&gt;
  &lt;component id="oldmodelreader" class="org.eclipse.emf.mwe.utils.Reader"
    uri="temp/old.model"
    firstElementOnly="true"
    ignoreMissingModel="true"
    modelSlot="oldmodel"            
  /&gt;
  
  &lt;!-- compute diff. --&gt;
  &lt;component id="compare" class="org.eclipse.xpand2.incremental.compare.EmfCompare"
    oldModelSlot="oldmodel"
    newModelSlot="model"
    diffModelSlot="diff"
  /&gt;

  &lt;!-- read trace model, produced by previous run. may not exist, so ignore missing model --&gt;
  &lt;component id="tracemodelreader" class="org.eclipse.emf.mwe.utils.Reader"
    uri="temp/trace.trace"
    firstElementOnly="true"
    ignoreMissingModel="true"
    modelSlot="oldtrace"            
  /&gt;

  &lt;!-- this is the actual incremental generation callback --&gt;
  &lt;component id="incremental"
      class="org.eclipse.xpand2.incremental.IncrementalGenerationCallback"
    diffModelSlot="diff"
    oldTraceModelSlot="oldtrace"
    newTraceModelSlot="trace"
  /&gt;
  
  &lt;!-- generate code --&gt;
  &lt;component id="generator" class="org.eclipse.xpand2.Generator"&gt;
    &lt;expand value="resources::templates::Test::Test FOR model" /&gt;
    &lt;outlet path="somewhere/" overwrite="true"/&gt;
    &lt;metaModel class="org.eclipse.xtend.typesystem.emf.EmfRegistryMetaModel" /&gt;
    &lt;vetoableCallback idRef="incremental" /&gt;
  &lt;/component&gt;
  
  &lt;!-- clean obsolete files --&gt;
  &lt;component id="cleaner" class="org.eclipse.xpand2.incremental.FileCleaner"&gt;
    &lt;oldTraceModelSlot value="oldtrace" /&gt;
    &lt;newTraceModelSlot value="trace" /&gt;
    &lt;outlet path="somewhere/" overwrite="true"/&gt;
  &lt;/component&gt;
  
  &lt;!-- write trace model --&gt;
  &lt;component id="tracemodelwriter" class="org.eclipse.emf.mwe.utils.Writer"
    modelSlot="trace"
    uri="temp/trace.trace"
  /&gt;      
  
  &lt;!-- make backup copy of model --&gt;
  &lt;component id="copier" class="org.eclipse.emf.mwe.utils.FileCopy"
    sourceFile="model/my.model"
    targetFile="temp/old.model"
  /&gt;
&lt;/workflow&gt;
</programlisting>

    </section>
    
  </section>

  <section id="incrementalGeneration_notes">
    <title>Additional Notes</title>
    
    <section id="incrementalGeneration_limitations">
      <title>Limitations</title>
      <para>
        The incremental generation process can only be used with EMF-based models.
        That's because all intermediate artifacts
        (<emphasis>diff model</emphasis> and <emphasis>trace model</emphasis>)
        which reference the original models are also stored as EMF models. It is
        therefore not possible to refer to other model formats. Moreover, you
        should make sure that your model has stable IDs for the individual
        model elements so that the model comparison doesn't run into any
        ambiguities.
      </para>
      
      <para>
      	Also note that at the moment, Xpand cannot track access to model elements
      	from JAVA extensions. This can lead to cases where a change in a specific
      	model element should trigger a specific (set of)
      	file(s) to be regenerated, but it actually doesn't.
      	That's because Xpand didn't know about the
      	model element being accessed during the original file generation,
      	so it has no indication that a regeneration is required. For that reason
      	you should try to access your model as much as possible from Xpand or
      	Xtend, and only resort to JAVA code when it is unavoidable.      	
      </para>      
    </section>
    
    <section id="incrementalGeneration_performance">
      <title>Performance Considerations</title>
      <para>
        The main performance benefits of incremental generation come from
        <emphasis>not</emphasis> doing things that are not necessary. Given
        the workflow from <xref linkend="incrementalGeneration_usage_callback" />,
        it may seem counterproductive to first
        perform a costly model comparison operation before it can even be
        determined whether a file has to be generated or not.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        While it is true that model comparison is a very expensive operation,
        it turns out that it still outweighs the costs of unnecessarily
        generating files, even if no postprocessing or subsequent compiler
        invocation is involved.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        That said, it is definitely preferrable to do without a model comparison
        and rather capture the changes to the model on-the-fly. So whenever
        you are working in a controlled environment, you may want to consider a
        customized integration of the generator invocation with the
        model editors.
      </para>
    </section>

  </section>
</chapter>